<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 <title>David Nadlinger</title>
 <link href="http://klickverbot.at/blog/tags/C++/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://klickverbot.at/"/>
 <updated>2023-08-07T18:22:35+01:00</updated>
 <id>http://klickverbot.at/blog/tags/C++/</id>
 <author>
   <name>David Nadlinger</name>
   <email>atom@klickverbot.at</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>STL Algorithms</title>
   <link href="http://klickverbot.at/blog/2010/04/stl-algorithms/"/>
   <updated>2010-04-20T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://klickverbot.at/blog/2010/04/stl-algorithms</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;While attending a workshop at &lt;a href=&quot;http://linz.linuxwochen.at&quot;&gt;Linuxwochen Linz&lt;/a&gt; recently, I found using &lt;code&gt;std::for_each&lt;/code&gt; and other algorithms from the C++ Standard Template library without even really thinking about it, much to the surprise of the other workshop attendants, which were, contrary to me, rather artists than coders. As I were thinking about the way my C++ coding style evolved over the years, I remembered that my use of &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;algorithm&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;s can be traced back to a single article on Dr. Dobb&amp;#8217;s: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.drdobbs.com/cpp/184401446&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;STL&lt;/span&gt; Algorithms vs. Hand-Written Loops&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The text was written by Scott Meyers almost ten years ago, but in my eyes, it is still a very good read on the topic. Highly recommended!&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Debugging KDE applications with gdb</title>
   <link href="http://klickverbot.at/blog/2009/01/debugging-kde-applications-with-gdb/"/>
   <updated>2009-01-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://klickverbot.at/blog/2009/01/debugging-kde-applications-with-gdb</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A pretty long time has passed since my last post here, and in the meantime I have jumped right into &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;KDE&lt;/span&gt; development myself. I have stumbled upon quite a few tricks and pitfalls that I will undoubtedly write about here some day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, I just want to share a little gem which I have discovered a few minutes ago: In &lt;code&gt;kdesdk/scripts&lt;/code&gt;, David Faure published a little script called &lt;code&gt;kde-devel-gdb&lt;/code&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;http://websvn.kde.org/trunk/KDE/kdesdk/scripts/kde-devel-gdb?view=markup&quot;&gt;view with WebSVN&lt;/a&gt;), which extends gdb with the ability to print the contents of several Qt containers, including the widely used &lt;code&gt;QString&lt;/code&gt;. Highly recommended!&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
</feed>
