<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 <title>David Nadlinger</title>
 <link href="http://klickverbot.at/blog/tags/KDE/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://klickverbot.at/"/>
 <updated>2019-08-03T18:16:12+01:00</updated>
 <id>http://klickverbot.at/blog/tags/KDE/</id>
 <author>
   <name>David Nadlinger</name>
   <email>atom@klickverbot.at</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Getting KDE's clippboard to work with Eclipse</title>
   <link href="http://klickverbot.at/blog/2009/05/getting-kdes-clippboard-to-work-with-eclipse/"/>
   <updated>2009-05-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://klickverbot.at/blog/2009/05/getting-kdes-clippboard-to-work-with-eclipse</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;For whatever reason, Eclipse does not work well with Klipper, the &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;KDE&lt;/span&gt; clipboard manager, in its default settings. The symptoms: Quite often, you copy a piece of text to the clipboard. When you try to paste it, it miraculously disappears and some old piece of clipboard content is pasted instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After simply trying to ignore the problem for some time, I searched and found a solution today: You have to disable the &lt;em&gt;»Prevent empty clipboard«&lt;/em&gt; setting in Klipper&amp;#8217;s configuration menu (which is accessible by right-clicking on the systray icon).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intuitive? Not to me…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;update&quot;&gt;Disabling the mentioned option might introduce some minor glitches to general clipboard usage (sometimes, the clipboard seems to empty itself). As those occur rather infrequently, I have not been able to find out why this happens, or even if this is connected to the configuration changes described in this post.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Duplicate »Translucency« KWin effect</title>
   <link href="http://klickverbot.at/blog/2009/04/duplicate-translucency-kwin-effect/"/>
   <updated>2009-04-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://klickverbot.at/blog/2009/04/duplicate-translucency-kwin-effect</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;For some time, the effect »Translucency« was listed twice in the KWin &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;KCM&lt;/span&gt; plugin list of my local &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;KDE&lt;/span&gt; setup (&lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;SVN&lt;/span&gt; trunk). One copy was actually working, the other was just producing error messages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, I finally had time to investigate the issue: The problem was caused by a stale &lt;code&gt;.desktop&lt;/code&gt; file in &lt;code&gt;share/kde4/services/kwin&lt;/code&gt; with the old name of the plugin (it was renamed from &lt;em&gt;maketransparent&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;translucency&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have no idea how this could happen, because I usually purge the whole &lt;code&gt;/opt/kde&lt;/code&gt; folder everytime I &lt;code&gt;svn up&lt;/code&gt; my &lt;code&gt;qt-copy&lt;/code&gt;, which I happen to do quite often…&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Debugging KDE applications with gdb</title>
   <link href="http://klickverbot.at/blog/2009/01/debugging-kde-applications-with-gdb/"/>
   <updated>2009-01-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://klickverbot.at/blog/2009/01/debugging-kde-applications-with-gdb</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A pretty long time has passed since my last post here, and in the meantime I have jumped right into &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;KDE&lt;/span&gt; development myself. I have stumbled upon quite a few tricks and pitfalls that I will undoubtedly write about here some day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, I just want to share a little gem which I have discovered a few minutes ago: In &lt;code&gt;kdesdk/scripts&lt;/code&gt;, David Faure published a little script called &lt;code&gt;kde-devel-gdb&lt;/code&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;http://websvn.kde.org/trunk/KDE/kdesdk/scripts/kde-devel-gdb?view=markup&quot;&gt;view with WebSVN&lt;/a&gt;), which extends gdb with the ability to print the contents of several Qt containers, including the widely used &lt;code&gt;QString&lt;/code&gt;. Highly recommended!&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>KHotkeys in KDE 4.1</title>
   <link href="http://klickverbot.at/blog/2008/11/khotkeys-in-kde-4-1/"/>
   <updated>2008-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://klickverbot.at/blog/2008/11/khotkeys-in-kde-4-1</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I just upgraded to Kubuntu 8.10 in order to have a look at shiny new &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;KDE&lt;/span&gt; 4. But amongst other minor annoyances, I had real trouble getting hotkeys to work. There are configuration options in the new System Settings panel (which is a huge regression compared to KControl by the way), but they seemed to have no effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After various attempts of fixing this problem myself, I finally found a (slightly hackish) solution: &lt;a href=&quot;http://ubuntuforums.org/showpost.php?p=5541572&amp;amp;postcount=9&quot;&gt;Re: Does khotkeys work on your &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;KDE&lt;/span&gt; 4.1?&lt;/a&gt;. Seems like &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;KDE&lt;/span&gt; 4.1 is still &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; beta&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>KDE Konsole corruption when Compiz is active</title>
   <link href="http://klickverbot.at/blog/2008/09/kde-konsole-corruption-when-compiz-is-active/"/>
   <updated>2008-09-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://klickverbot.at/blog/2008/09/kde-konsole-corruption-when-compiz-is-active</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;On my laptop I&amp;#8217;m currently running Kubuntu 8.04 (Hardy Heron). For additional eye candy goodness I am using the &lt;code&gt;compiz-fusion&lt;/code&gt; package from the Kubuntu repositories. Surprisingly, even on the laptop hardware (Asus V1S) everything went smooth out of the box – I could even manage to find some drivers for the webcam and for the finger print scanner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, everything worked fine except for one little detail: When I had an active Konsole session on one cube face, for example a log file, and continued to work on another side of the cube, the Konsole output would often be broken when I switched back to it. It would look as if the output had been scrolled, but the non-scrolled output hadn&amp;#8217;t been cleared from the window. This problem could be fixed by forcing the window to refresh, e.g. by switching to another (Konsole) tab.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In their 169.XX driver series, nVidia added a config option called &lt;code&gt;UseCompositeWrapper&lt;/code&gt;, which can help to sort out this kind of redraw problems. Fortunately, enabling this via adding the following line to the &lt;code&gt;Device&lt;/code&gt; section of my &lt;code&gt;xorg.conf&lt;/code&gt; was enough to solve the problem:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Option &quot;UseCompositeWrapper&quot; &quot;true&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
</feed>
