<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 <title>David Nadlinger</title>
 <link href="http://klickverbot.at/blog/tags/Phobos/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://klickverbot.at/"/>
 <updated>2019-08-04T08:00:07+01:00</updated>
 <id>http://klickverbot.at/blog/tags/Phobos/</id>
 <author>
   <name>David Nadlinger</name>
   <email>atom@klickverbot.at</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Random D development news</title>
   <link href="http://klickverbot.at/blog/2011/04/random-d-development-news/"/>
   <updated>2011-04-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://klickverbot.at/blog/2011/04/random-d-development-news</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;During the last couple of weeks, I didn&amp;#8217;t really find time to update this blog. Nevertheless, however, I was able to spare some time for work on a couple open source projects related to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://d-programming-language.org&quot;&gt;D programming language&lt;/a&gt;. But first, let me quickly summarize some great changes that will be in the next &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;DMD&lt;/span&gt; release:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don Clugston has basically &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/D-Programming-Language/dmd/pull/23&quot;&gt;re-implemented &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;CTFE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to fix a whole slew of compile-time function execution bugs, among which is the dreaded &lt;a href=&quot;http://d.puremagic.com/issues/show_bug.cgi?id=1330&quot;&gt;bug 1330&lt;/a&gt;. There are still some regressions compared to &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;DMD&lt;/span&gt; 2.052 (like &lt;a href=&quot;http://lists.puremagic.com/pipermail/dmd-internals/2011-April/001448.html&quot;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt;, which breaks QtD), but apart from those, it&amp;#8217;s a big step towards getting &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;CTFE&lt;/span&gt; out of the »experimental feature« category. The new architecture will also make implementing reference types easier, but this is still a long way off. Then next &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;DMD&lt;/span&gt;/Phobos release will also include the new &lt;a href=&quot;http://cis.jhu.edu/~dsimcha/d/phobos/std_parallelism.html&quot;&gt;std.parallelism&lt;/a&gt; module by David Simcha, some GC optimizations and a large amount of other improvements (among which is the addition of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/D-Programming-Language/dmd/commit/2e261cd640e5266c569ad224ffbfe229a0315d97&quot;&gt;parent trait&lt;/a&gt;, so that QtD doesn&amp;#8217;t need a patched &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;DMD&lt;/span&gt; any longer) – due to the GitHub migration and the larger part of x86_64 support being done, the perceived development speed in the core community really went up a notch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for my own (insignificant, compared to the above) contributions, I did some work on &lt;a href=&quot;http://dsource.org/projects/ldc&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;LDC&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; during the last few days, porting it to &lt;a href=&quot;http://llvm.org/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;LLVM&lt;/span&gt; 2.9&lt;/a&gt; and bringing the front-end in sync with &lt;a href=&quot;http://digitalmars.com/d/1.0/changelog.html&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;DMD&lt;/span&gt; 1.067&lt;/a&gt; – you can find the changes in the default branch over at &lt;a href=&quot;https://bitbucket.org/lindquist/ldc&quot;&gt;Bitbucket&lt;/a&gt;. The &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;DMD&lt;/span&gt; updates also contained some changes to the varargs &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;ABI&lt;/span&gt; on x86_64 and other areas of the runtime interface, which I didn&amp;#8217;t merge yet, because it would require an update to Tango as well. I am not aware of any regressions so far (see the &lt;a href=&quot;/code/ldc/&quot;&gt;DStress results&lt;/a&gt;), but feel free to ping me in case of any problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were also some updates and bug fixes to D support in &lt;a href=&quot;http://swig.org&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;SWIG&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, most notably support for the &lt;a href=&quot;http://swig.org/Doc2.0/D.html#D_nspace&quot;&gt;nspace feature&lt;/a&gt;, which allows you to map C++ namespaces to D packages/modules (it doesn&amp;#8217;t work for free functions and global variables yet, but this is a general &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;SWIG&lt;/span&gt; restriction that could be easily lifted, just ask me if you need it). There was another &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;SWIG&lt;/span&gt; release in the meantime, version 2.0.3, but it was only a »quick backup« by the maintainer before he merged some intrusive Python changes. I was caught pretty much off-guard by it and had no time for real testing and thus, it contains some bugs (mainly related to nspace support when split-proxy mode is not activated, thanks to Jonathan Pfau for the reports) – please use &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;SVN&lt;/span&gt; trunk instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another little project I recently worked on is &lt;a href=&quot;/code/units/&quot;&gt;std.units&lt;/a&gt;, an units of measurement implementation for D. This topic came up several times on the NG previously, and every time it was suggested to add units support with Phobos, so I have merged the work into my Phobos fork. Please note, however, that this is in no way a formal review request yet. There are still a couple of items left on my to-do list, but before I am tackling the remaining issues, I&amp;#8217;d greatly appreciate some feedback (see the thread on the D newsgroup, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.digitalmars.com/webnews/newsgroups.php?art_group=digitalmars.D&amp;amp;article_id=134590&quot; title=&quot;Phobos?&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;RFC&lt;/span&gt;: Units of measurement for D&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, a personal note: Yesterday, I received notice that I was accepted to work on my &lt;a href=&quot;/code/gsoc/thrift&quot;&gt;Apache Thrift project&lt;/a&gt; under the umbrella of Digital Mars as part of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.google-melange.com/gsoc/homepage/google/gsoc2011&quot;&gt;Google Summer of Code 2011&lt;/a&gt; – thanks a lot to everybody who supported my proposals for their trust in me! I know that the expectations are high, and will do my very best to live up to them.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
</feed>
